In Unity we can create a custom inspector to control
Unity ではカスタムインスペクターを作成して
which data from our scripts is visible
スクリプト中の どのデータを表示するか
and how it is represented in the editor.
そしてエディター上でどう表示するかを制御できます
That ability to extend the editor in this way
エディターを拡張できるということは
gives us a lot of power and flexibility with our scripts
スクリプトがより強力かつ柔軟に使えるということで
and the resulting workflow.
ひいてはワークフローの改良にもつながります
Let's say we had a levelling system
たとえばレベルアップシステムを作っているとしましょう
where every time a character earned 750 experience points
これは経験値を 750 ポイント獲得すると
they gained a new level.
レベルがひとつ上がるシステムであるとします
This is easy enough to calculate in the beginning
レベルが低いうちは計算も簡単ですが
but it could be a bit cumbersome as characters
高レベルになるにつれてだんだんと
get to higher levels.
計算がめんどくさくなってきます
Luckily we can create a custom
そこでカスタムインスペクターを
inspector to make this much simpler.
使って この作業を簡単にしてみましょう
Here we have a script called LevelScript.
ここに LevelScript というスクリプトがあります
This script represents the experience based
このスクリプトが先ほどの経験値ベースの
levelling system mentioned before.
レベルアップシステムです
In the script we first have a variable named experience
スクリプトで最初に目に入るのが experience 変数ですね
which will contain the total amount of experience
この関数はキャラクターが獲得した
a character has accumulated.
経験値の累計を格納します
Next we have a property named Level.
次に Level というプロパティがあります
We can see that this property takes the current
このプロパティは 現在の経験値を取り
experience value and returns the level equivalent.
対応するレベルを返します
For more information on properties
プロパティの詳細については
see the lesson on properties linked below.
下記リンク先にあるプロパティのレッスンをご覧ください
In Unity we have an empty game object
さて空っぽのゲームオブジェクトを配置して
with the LevelScript attached.
それに LevelScript をアタッチしてみました
Notice how we can see the experience
Experience（経験値）プロパティがインスペクターに
property in the inspector.
表示されているのが見えますね
It is easy to calculate the level when our experience is 0.
経験値が 0 ならレベルを計算するのも簡単ですが
But what if it was 49865?
49865 だったらどうでしょう?
Let's customise the inspector to show
ここでインスペクターをカスタマイズして
the level for us.
レベルを表示してみましょう
In order to customise the inspector we need
インスペクターをカスタマイズするにはまずエディターの
to make a folder to place our editor scripts in.
スクリプトを格納するフォルダを作成する必要があります
Unity requires that this folder is named
Unity に認識させるためこのフォルダの名前は
Editor.
Editor としてください
Inside the editor folder we will create a new script.
そしてフォルダ内に新規スクリプトを作成します
This script will contain our custom inspector.
このスクリプトにカスタムインスペクターを含めます
It can have any name,
名前は自由に付けられますが
but for the sake of this example we will
今回は内容に沿って
call it LevelScriptEditor.
LevelScriptEditor としましょう
In the LevelScriptEditor
それではこの LevelScriptEditor に
we can begin writing our custom inspector.
カスタムインスペクターを書いていきます
Before we begin writing any editor specific code
エディター固有のコードを書くときはまず
we must first declare that we are using the
UnityEditor 名前空間を使うことを
UnityEditor namespace.
宣言しなくてはいけません
For more information on namespaces
名前空間の詳細については
see the lesson on namespaces linked below.
下記リンク先にある名前空間のレッスンをご覧ください
Next we need to inherit from editor
次に継承元を MonoBehaviour から
instead of monobehaviour.
Editor に変更します
This in effect is how we extend the editor.
エディタの拡張は基本的にこうして行います
For more information on inheritance
継承の詳細については
see the lesson on inheritance linked below.
下記リンク先にある継承のレッスンをご覧ください
From here we need to give our custom
さてここからは カスタムインスペクターに
inspector an attribute to tell it which
属性を与えて どのスクリプトを
script we are customising.
カスタマイズしているのかを示します
The syntax for doing this starts with a
構文はまず開き角カッコ  続けて
open square bracket followed by the
キーワードCustomEditor
keyword CustomEditor and parenthesis.
そしてカッコ
Inside the parenthesis we use the keyword
カッコの中にはキーワード
typeOf to specify the type.
typeOf で型を指定します
And then we put the name of our script
そしてその中にさらにカッコの対を作り
in another set of parenthesis.
スクリプトの名前を入力します
We can see that in this example
この例では ご覧のとおり
the script we are customising is the LevelScript.
カスタマイズするのは LevelScript です
We end the line with a closed square bracket.
そして行を  閉じ角カッコで締めます
Inside our LevelScriptEditor class
続いて LevelScriptEditor クラスの内部に
we create the method public override void
メソッド public override void OnInspectorGUI
OnInspectorGUI
を作ります
This is the method that is called every time the
このメソッドはインスペクターが Unity 上で描画される際に
inspector is drawn inside Unity.
毎回呼び出されます
For more information on what the override
override キーワードの
keyword is doing
挙動の詳細については
see the lesson on overriding linked below.
下記リンク先にあるオーバーライドのレッスンをご覧ください
At this point the inspector for the
これで LevelScript のインスペクターが
LevelScript has been modified.
変更されました
If we go back in to Unity we can see
この状態で Unity に戻ると
that we no longer see any properties of
スクリプトのプロパティがひとつも
the script in the inspector view.
インスペクタービューに表示されないのがわかります
Since this is not very useful
これではぜんぜん便利でないので
let's continue writing our custom inspector.
カスタマイズを進めていきましょう
Back in the LevelScriptEditor
LevelScriptEditor に戻って
we will want to create some fields for the inspector.
インスペクターで表示するフィールドを作ってみます
We automatically have a reference to our LevelScript object
OnInspectorGUI メソッドの内部には自動的に LevelScript
named target inside the OnInspectorGUI method.
オブジェクトへの参照である target が含まれます
This isn't useable until we cast it in to
しかしこれは適切な型の変数に
an appropriately typed variable however.
キャストするまでは使えません
To do this we will create a
なのでまず myLevelScript という
LevelScript variable named myLevelScript
LevelScript 変数を作り
and set it equal to the inherited variable target.
継承した変数 target とイコールでつなぎます
Finally we will cast the variable
そして最後に target 変数を
target as a LevelScript variable
LevelScript 変数としてキャストします
by writing LevelScript in parenthesis next to it.
これはカッコで囲んだ LevelScript を隣に書いて表現します
We want our inspector to show two pieces of information.
さてここでインスペクターに表示したい情報は
The amount of experience the character has,
キャラクターの獲得した経験値合計と
and the current level of the character.
現在のレベルの 2 つです
We can create an integer field in the inspector
インスペクターに int フィールドを作るときは
using the EditorGUILayout class.
EditorGUILayout クラスを使います
The syntax for this starts with the classname
構文は  最初にクラス名
EditorGUILayout, followed by a period
EditorGUILayout 続けて.（ピリオド）
and then the method IntField
そしてメソッド IntField
followed by parenthesis.
最後にカッコ
Inside the parenthesis we specify the name of the field
カッコの中にはフィールド名と
and the value of the field.
フィールドの値を指定します
In this case we want the field to be named Experience
今回はフィールド名に Experience（経験値）
and the value to be the value of the experience variable
値に myLevelScript の experience 変数の値を
of our myLevelScript.
指定します
Since we want this field to be able to write back
このフィールドに experience 変数への書き込みも
to our Experience variable we set the entire line
させたいので  行全体を myLevelScript.experience と
equal to myLevelScript.experience.
イコールでつなぎます
We follow a similar process for the Level field.
Level フィールドもだいたい同じように処理していきます
This time however we will be using
ただし今回は
the LabelField method of the EditorGUILayout class.
EditorGUILayout クラスの LabelField メソッドを使います
A label is a read-only control
ラベルは読み取り専用なので
so we do not have to worry about the user
ユーザーがインスペクター上でレベルを
attempting to manually adjust the level in the inspector.
手動入力してしまうことは起きません
Inside the parenthesis of the LabelField method
LabelField メソッドのカッコ内には
we parse in the name Level
Level という名前と
and the value myLevelScript.Level.
値 myLevelScript.Level を指定します
Since a label control requires a string as a value
ただしラベルのコントロールは文字列である必要があるので
we will call the ToString method
ここで Level プロパティに対して
of the Level property to turn it
ToString メソッドを使い
in to a string.
文字列に変換します
At this point our custom inspector is complete.
これでカスタムインスペクターは完成です
We can go back in to Unity to see the result.
さっそく Unity に戻って確認してみましょう
In the inspector we can see that
ご覧のとおり インスペクターには
when our experience is 49865
経験値が 49865 のとき
our level is 66.
レベルは 66 と表示されました
Furthermore we can see that as
そして  この経験値のフィールドで
we adjust the experience value
値を変更していくと
the inspector automatically tells us the level.
自動的にレベルの値も変更されていきます
By customising the editor for our scripts
このようにスクリプト向けにエディターを
we can simplify and automate
カスタマイズすると 手動では面倒くさい
many of our otherwise cumbersome tasks.
さまざまな事柄が自動化できるわけです